so this is the first rebel wisdom Q&A we
announced earlier in the week and asked
you guys to put your questions
underneath the video and then to vote up
the questions that you wanted answered
so what we've discovered is that our
audience is far smarter than us and
they've asked us questions that we maybe
won't be able to answer but we'll do
what we can so we're basically going to
time this and it will be an hour and
we'll answer definitely answer the first
12 questions and then we'll start going
down below that and work out depending
on how much time we've got that will
decide how many questions have been
asked to answer so first and so the 12
top questions we're not necessarily
going to answer them the order that they
were that they're they were ranked but
we're going to answer all all 12 of them
and starting with the ones that we know
that we can answer moving on to the ones
that we're really struggling with you
can't decide yourselves when that moment
comes hmm so Allie why do you use the
Black Sun as a logo what does it mean to
you cuz it looks cool Cleo the first
thing to say it's not the place it's not
a Black Sun or no Sun it's the eye and
the triangle yes exactly yeah
and for me the eye represents the I
guess the transformative power of true
knowledge inner knowledge truth in
general and yeah it's so combined it has
that sense for me and I know what are
your feelings on our logo I so from the
beginning when we were trying to put the
logo together the idea was I was
listening to a lot of Jordan Peterson
stuff at the time and the idea of the it
was the eye and the pyramid the pyramid
or the the triangle being truth logos
the dominance hierarchy all that sort of
stuff
and the eye meaning awareness and the
eye there's actually a little clip that
I might dig out and see if we can play
where I
the logo - Jordan Peterson during my
first interview and he was like yeah
that's perfect you've got it because
it's the eye it's the awareness but it's
the eye and the Sun in the pyramid that
you worship not the pyramid itself it's
the regenerating factor that the
awareness is consciousness effectively
it's the consciousness that is that is
then able to update the structure that
we should be worshipping not the
destructor itself don't know if you saw
the logo that we've put together forever
wisdom and recognize the eye and yep and
the triangle yeah perfect we were
looking for an abstract kind of way that
didn't look too Illuminati there's a
little bit Illuminati but not quite
right so much yeah well that's the thing
is that it's the it's the Sun in the
pyramid that you worship not the pyramid
right because the Sun is the thing that
in both senses that stops it from being
the patriarchy so that's the thing that
you can have a relationship with that it
transcends the dominance hierarchy
itself yeah it is it is it's it's it's
it like in the Lion King that there's
that little bird Zazu well he flies
above everything sees everything that's
the eye that's the Egyptian eye it's
outside the structure it's the thing
that moves up and down the structure and
it repairs it that's what consciousness
does in your body it's it moves up and
down levels of of reality let's say and
and alters them so in it's so it's
outside the structure and it's also the
thing that gives rise to the structure
but the structure also gives rise to it
that's why there's Trinitarian ideas in
Christianity you know there's the father
and the son and they're mutually causal
think well how can that be well the son
gives birth to the father obviously
because boys turn into men but the
father also gives birth to the son and
so that's part of the reason that those
Trinitarian ideas exist yeah when we
were putting the logo together the only
kind of brief that we were kind of clear
on is it can't look too Illuminati
because obviously you're starting as you
start to the pyramids and I
getting into kind of the dollar bill
territory in your life okay it can't be
Illuminati and the head and he actually
got it done and it was like yeah that
looks perfect it's great I'm one of the
first comments workers why why is your
logo there but my favorite comment ever
or no in our films is what was it it
salute your logo is Illuminati as
but you seem legit which i think is
about as good as it gets
yeah really yeah I really love that idea
I'm just think remembering something
that was actually involve under clays
sermon but don't think we've put out
this particular bit of it that really
stuck with me
the whole idea of being able to step out
of the structure of the hierarchy
whatever it is and regenerate it and
have a different perspective on it is
really it's a really deep idea you know
he talked about Jesus washing the feet
of the disciples of his disciples and
that being a an action that kind of took
him or could have inverted everything on
his head and took him out of the
dominance hierarchy game altogether
really interesting and there's the the
top becomes the bottom and that's the
kind of regeneration of the structure
exactly yeah and then there's this is
very famous alchemical image called the
I really hope I pronounced it right but
we can we can probably put it up on
screen the telling me Ron tell a Marion
I think with a lot of people will be
aware of it it's the kind of the
initiate climbing through one sphere
into the heavens if you neutral I'm
talking about they're kind of on there
yeah we can put it up though but I love
that kind of alchemical idea of
knowledge in general can give us a
completely new perspective on reality
and for me the logo holds some of that
kind of symbolism in it as well go so
that's the story the logo so question
two questions
yeah so question two is from sorry so
question one by the way was from the
dashing rogue question two is from and
I'm going to try and pronounce this
correctly apologies it was wrong land be
art so what do you to see as the Telos
or end of all this Peterson slash
intellectual dark web stuff what is the
goal to ultimately justify and direct
this collective intellectual endeavor
hmm great question it's a great question
because I think a lot of people involved
in this conversation probably have
different ideas about what the end goal
is I think Peterson I mean the end it's
like at the moment the ID w's end goal
or the the goal right now for the idea W
is to carve out a space to have a
conversation where it goes from there I
think different members of the IDW have
different concepts of where it goes from
there and I think that there is a hope
yeah they do hope that it can that
having that conversation can begin to
find the solutions that will what would
you say kind of change society or deal
with deal with the essential threats
that we're dealing with I mean they've
got very big ideas definitely yeah and I
especially look like specially I'm
thinking the Weinstein
yeah ticular yeah Weinstein and Bret
Weinstein they do they seem to be
holding one of the the most farsighted
pieces in the IDW yeah I think Peterson
has a slightly different focus he's much
more focused on the individual and the
the transformative power of coming into
your true alignment yet then as a
priority and then that itself becomes
the he sees that as the main seat of
transformation rather than the
structural in that yeah and I'm still
not entirely clear on his kind of the
relationship between that and that and
the widest structures of society yeah
I'm not entirely sure either on that
point yeah I agree with you I think one
aspect of it is definitely that the kind
of conversation that is happening now in
the IDW gets integrated into the wider I
guess into lots of different
institutions that are you know which is
something arguably that needs to happen
for us to be able to move forward
effectively so in that sense that's
I hope what in a sense maybe it's
happening already or the beginnings of
it are personally I mean in terms of the
question of where's the end of it I
don't know I have no idea where I would
like it to go is to quite is to open the
space for a more integral way of seeing
the world so that's something for
example like sam Harris Jordan Peterson
though it's not one winning its that
both it's holding a kind of resolution
that allows for different aspects that
allows for the material that allows for
the spiritual that allows for the
biological and the artistic and kind of
you know for me that's what the great
intellectual awakening is it's it's
creating a space that is less polarized
not just politically but also in our our
values of yeah what we value is good
thinking in a sense I mean it's an
interesting question as well because I
have a sense of where I feel the
intellectual integration would go and
also a sense of that actually it needs
to be more than intellectual integration
it needs to incorporate sort of the more
embodied forms of knowing the more
transformational spaces so and I'm still
not sure whether I'm projecting that on
to the IDW conversation like assuming
that they would also share a similar
idea because I don't think they
necessarily do but I see that there's a
great quote that begins a book the
epilogue of passion of the Western mind
by Richert Arnaz brought by Robert
Bellah and he talks about we may be seen
in the paraphrase and maybe I can put it
up on mine up on screen but something
like we may be seeing the beginnings of
a reintegration of consciousness it will
not be based on any single unit univocal
understanding of reality it'll recognize
that we have to ship between different
imaginative vocabularies and that we
have a propensity to fit to slip into
one literal interpretation of the world
so we need to be eternally alert to that
so it's this sense that Peterson's
Jungian map work
yeah Brett's evolutionary map works they
map onto each other they reconcile like
lots of different people in the IDW have
different parts of the puzzle I also
think that's probably a few other people
who are not considered part of the IDW
at the moment that probably if that is
the nature of the conversation will have
to come into it at some point kind of
future like I think for example Jamie
wheel we didn't interview with I think
is still one of the best interviews
we've done is holding such an important
piece of what that what the embody
transformational work that we would have
to do to be able to yeah ultimately the
one we're stuck and not seeing things
from another person's perspective or
we're not able to understand all there's
some kind of block often it's because
we're we're holding on to something at a
deeper level like a psycho like this you
know some belief or some yeah childhood
conditioning or something like that it's
like and and that ultimately like that's
the only genuine reconciliation I can
see is when we're bringing in the whole
person or when bringing in yeah we're
bringing in to the other levels of
knowledge as well as just the
intellectual yeah I'm also just closing
on that point I'm gonna slightly
contradict myself from earlier because
yeah the I think it's about the
reenactment of the world is this a
phrase that kind of used sometimes about
bringing a meaning back into the world
so at the same time as holding a more
integral perspective so it's not
necessarily that there's this
equivalency of like everything has a
piece of the puzzle that's not
necessarily true I think truth is still
the kind of thing that determines the
direction and we're all the maps
converge so I just wanted to clarify
that and yeah that is there's also you
know what you were just talking about
being able to hold different
perspectives at the same time that feels
that feels absolutely essential and for
me it's completely wrapped up in
creating a more psychologically psycho
spiritually aware
society in a sense orally or you know
intellectual movement let's say as well
cool okay Ally I would love this is this
question is from Adele Sumi adults are
summe I would like to hear what pieces
of art you regard as a highest human
achievement that you know of no no
messing around in category of raising
oneself closer to God and your opinion
on music and your perspective on its
effects on consciousness individual and
social so it's for a bit cheeky it's
it's meaty I'm I'm gonna be a bit cheeky
and not answer it with one particular
piece of art because I tried I kind of
sat there and thought I'm a lot more I'm
not so into visual art I can really
appreciate it but for me there are that
really that I really connect with tends
to be literature and music so I'm gonna
blend a few things together so pieces of
art you regard as a highest human
achievement then you know all that in
the category of raising one's self
closer to God so I think music has that
power maybe more than and it'll be
different for every person but for me
more than most other art forms music has
this especially music song live or song
all together or play together so I play
traditional Irish music I can pubs and
even that I wouldn't say that's like a
deep mystical experience but it's really
a beautiful flow state so in that sense
like music really yeah really gets me
into a state of flow and I think most
people especially in a really good
concert or gig or whatever it is that's
why you know actually Jamie real talks
about that I'm stealing fire it's like
that's one of the reasons we really love
music you know it gets us into that into
that space I'm also big fan of visionary
art so art that's created based on the
visionary experience which might be
drug-induced it might be you know some
people do from lucid dreams it can be
all sorts I think that's really profound
and powerful because that's coming
directly from an altered space and it's
kind of made with that space in mind I
think art is I've always been really
interested in the idea of
art as a drug and how can art become and
is in some way a drug in and of itself
that it actually puts you in a different
state and I find that concept about art
in general I think any art that manages
to do that and people have that
experience looking at Renaissance
paintings as well you know so I think
that's when it's that's when it plays
that role of getting us in your words
you know closer to God or closer to the
transcendent or whatever you want to
call it so yeah that's my scattered
thinking on that very deep question your
thoughts I'm gonna just throw a little
curveball in and say that what I find
myself spending most of my time
listening to and I I i also think music
this there's something about music that
is it also fits with what peterson talks
about that out that meaning is a primary
sanitation yeah well meaning is not
something that happens secondarily
meaning or something that there's very
very prime at primary yeah and music i
think speaks to that because it it's a
it's a believe oak meaning and it but
able to evoke emotion was reliably and
it's like why does it poke those
emotions it's it's it's somehow tapping
quite directly into yeah in time meaning
systems some of the curveball i was
going to throw in is that I'm a massive
fan of rap and I love I love the fact
that it is there's something about the
way it just ties everything together
that's the port the thing that they're
often rapping about is more and more
lyrically dextrous ways of talking about
how in the flow in that particular
moment they are like it's very self
referential but they're I'm very
performative and the best rap really
conscious really self-aware really kind
of just in that state of flow I find
just really powerful I love it and of
the best piece of art that I've been
most impressed with the pieces of art
that we're most impressed with over the
last couple of years probably Kendrick
Lamar's good kid maad city and then
to pimp a butterfly I wasn't as taken
with damn although he kind of won a lot
more Awards for that but in good kid
maad city in particular there is it's
got the depth of a novel it's got the
depth of a characterization and the
metaphors the way that it refers it
basically about one day and it
continually refers back to itself it's
an absolute masterpiece and I was
obsessed as you're probably very like a
couple years ago it's like obsessed with
Kendrick Lamar I was telling everyone
who glisten look this is a masterpiece
this is listen this is this is a great
novel in musical form and I feel a
little bit vindicated like people were
just saying to us with kind of the model
and he want to pull that he's now won a
Pulitzer for yeah for the his work and
that I'm like yeah I'm glad that he's
getting that kind of recognition I'm
glad people are actually realizing that
there's a there's an incredible lyrical
storyteller there and I don't I don't
see many other artists on that level at
the moment doing what he's doing but
yeah oh oh yeah I won't say that's the
highest human achievement I know of but
that's good yeah five and Julian what
says I'm wondering how you distinguish
your and presumably Peterson's position
on religion from people like Sam Harris
on one hand and people like pull them to
clay on the other I assume you'd agree
more with Harris than the vendor clay
about the ontological status of events
like the resurrection if so what is the
real difference between your positions
do you see psychological value and
religion at sam Harris does not thanks
also a very good question yeah and I
mean yeah it's a really good question
and at this point I assume you would
agree more with Harris than with van der
clay about the ontological status of
events like the resurrection so speaking
for me personally probably yes I would
say to that
if
however it's a complex question because
something like the resurrection gets
into the world of you know myth and
symbolism and what does the resurrection
actually represent psychologically so
you know that's kind of where where my
interests lie in terms of religion like
the word religion is also a tricky one
because my spiritual practice is usually
based around phenomenology it's actually
it's experiential so I'm not I'm not
really big on belief I think faith is
important but that's like a whole other
topic there's some things that are
unknowable in a sense but belief I've
always been skeptical of because for me
it's about having a religious experience
or say a spiritual experience or a peak
mystical experience or whatever it might
be and bringing my own individual
sovereignty to integrating it and
figuring out okay how do i how me my ego
how do i integrate this what do I make
of this and that's always been my my way
so I probably have yeah I probably do
have a I'm not sure if I'm like van der
clay or Harris in my perspective on that
particular thing yeah hand over to you
mmm I I feel like I'm only starting now
to really grapple with the Christian
story in any kind of meaningful way like
we talked to Paul Lander clay I talked
with Jonathan page oh the other night
and he he had a sort of because because
I also heard a few people say that it
all hinges on the resurrection and I I'm
not entirely sure what that means at the
moment but I've heard more than a few
people talk about Christianity in that
way but if the resurrection is not true
then the whole of Christianity falls
apart
I don't quite understand all of that yet
but what I and then when I when I asked
that to Jonathan he said something that
about that the resurrection is something
that happens at the end of time and it
happens now and there's some inter
relation between the resurrection is
always with us and is always happening
in some sense I'm paraphrasing probably
badly but I think I I think I have a
felt sense of what he might mean by that
and he was also like I've been very
taken by by the Jungian explanation or
the Jungian examination of of Jesus as
an archetype as kind of in a way it
doesn't really matter whether he existed
as a person because what he embodies and
represents is the ideal person the ideal
human and whether that ideal human lived
and whether that ideal came whether
there have been other people who had the
same level of spiritual awareness and
spiritual presence that he did there is
a sort of moment where that archetype
entered the world fully formed and it it
means something to all of us and it has
had a huge impact on the direction of
Western culture in the direction of the
world so the whole idea at the very
least has a reality there's a really
deep resonance and reality the actual
state of whether it applies to us to a
person what that how that in a way I'm
joking that's a particularly interesting
question mmm because the interesting
questions are what is the nature of this
archetype what is the nature of this
yeah this archetype that has that has
been so influential and I think I don't
yet know enough I'm looking forward to
kind of having more conversations with
people who maybe have more of a deeper
understanding of what it means to them
yeah I think the problem with wood
religion is when they dispense with that
when it becomes a dogma it becomes just
a set of a set of yeah when the dead
word stops being infused with the living
sort of inquiry hmm that's where I start
to sort of lose patience and they
talking cold and it's like I don't
really understand what that's about but
yeah I think I think one other thing
another interesting thing that Jonathan
says we're gonna put out Jonathan
Pedro's talk we talk for quite a bit
longer than the bit we've put out so far
but at the same Harris section so we've
got another section talking about the
value of organized religion and yeah his
hairs on my history with Christianity
and what I remember from that is his
resistance to the Jungian analysis
because he didn't think the religious
should be reduced to the psychological
and I like I'm again paraphrasing but
that it's it's not a case of explaining
it because if it's if it's religiously
archetypal II true then the
psychological will be a subset of the
kind of the deeper reality if that makes
sense yeah yeah definitely I mean this
is a huge topic I feel like we could
talk about a lot I mean I have a few
things bubbling away but I think because
we have more content coming out on this
and we'll do another Q&A I'm going to
sit and Mull it over because it's so big
actually and maybe move to the next
question
yeah which is ah so this is a short one
from Peter heads I have a glance out
right have you read any CS Lewis
apologetics if so what did you think no
I haven't and I hated them I also
haven't read them and I also hidden it
no and we I I certainly haven't I did
look it up to see if it would be
possible to read in time but it seems
like it's quite in
and there's a lot to it so thanks for
bringing it up it's really good to be
aware of but unfortunately can't can't
add anything to that mm-hmm there is I
don't know
obviously I guess most people know CS
Lewis the author of Lyon which in the
Wardrobe which is a deeply kind of
allegorical very Christian story I've
heard about these before and I think it
yeah I'd like to check them out as well
all I know about him is that he was part
of a very interesting group of there was
a lot going on in the sort of 30s 40s
50s I think yeah in I think it was
Cambridge yeah there was a group called
the Inklings Tolkien was part of it CS
Lewis was part of it couple other people
were part of it sort of the very sort of
English eccentric intellectual really
trying to understand what the what the
deeper structure of these kind of
mythological stories was yeah and that
I've always been sort of quite attracted
to to learning a bit more about it like
them and I think TS Eliot's as well like
a really fascinating character because
he was even atheist who wrote these
amazing poems like The Hollow Men and
then had a Christian then became a
Christian later in life there's a lot of
there was a lot of interesting stuff and
in those life stories I think yeah
that's an interesting processed here
Elia because modern is it was very much
a kind of disenchantment of the world
it's called The Waste Land the ways that
yeah exactly yeah and and a you know
response to world were one in many ways
as well around the that the roots of
post-modernism come from that of
everything we held sacred never came
have seemed to be safe and secure was
kind of blown to by World War one
and then the kind of grappling with that
modernist I studied modernist poetry
quite a bit and it's got kind of a bleak
Beauty to it but I didn't actually kind
of forgotten that about Eliot that then
there's this kind of revival of meaning
that probably I don't know I imagined
was like you would have grass with both
hands and a lot of people probably
would have at that time as well it's an
interesting thing - yeah yeah that it's
also interesting that that seems to be
the last time maybe because of the the
nature of the times and maybe that's
what we're going through again is some
sort of sense of a lot of people
compared this time to a bit like the
sort of 1930s and 1960s maybe that's
when you see these these spiritual
awakenings and religious awakenings yeah
so if you know the answers no to your
question I have to get a nice to kill
five minutes out of it so what are we
number seven liver so could you is it
male you it's you there's some yeah yeah
could you do interviews with two people
who have different views on the deep
issues I think these make the most
interesting interactions and if you do
it
I think conversation is preferable to a
debate watching your content also in
Israel keep up the good work
don't forget muscle the muscle emoticon
I don't have a motor oh yeah you do that
yes definitely and I think it's a really
good shout so we're gonna give your
name's it's in Hebrew and we neither of
us can read Hebrew but yeah doing
interviews of two people have different
views and deep issues so I think it's a
great format I think again that requires
this kind of it's part of why the
intellectual dark web works you know
there has to be an embodiment on the
human level of a certain degree of kind
of guess what Jordan green will call
inner sovereignty to be able to hold a
space and not get into reactivity I
think a lot of people can do that so I
think it's really yeah great
we've been talking a little bit about
different ways to do that already
so yeah yeah different views and the
deeper issues yeah I think it's
interesting to me too
yeah kind of wonder whether like so far
we've been interviewing the people that
we want to interview that we're
interested in we like their ideas I I'm
always interested in who are the people
who push you
conversations forward I'm not personally
interested in interviewing someone when
I know what they're going to say hmm I
don't find that particularly so I
wouldn't I wouldn't want to interview
people with different ideas just for the
sake of it I think it would have to be
when both of them had a had a sense of
that there was a genuine inquiry and a
genuine to the possibility for evolution
of their ideas yeah definitely there's
something of in Zen there's beginner's
mind where you come without any
preconceptions and there's a kind of
lack of attachment to your own position
and that actually is kind of rare
sometimes you know it in academia for
example it's very rare if you had two
academics defending something that
they'd wrote their thesis on spent 30
years lecturing and the worth trying to
do what they should be doing is finding
some kind of truth that allows their
ideas to burn away I think it's very
unlikely that that it's very likely when
that happens yeah yeah yeah I think the
more public profile someone has the
harder it is to yeah she'd be generative
for sure and next question is from G
Thomas a few episodes back you guys were
talking about some of the negative press
surrounding the intellectual dark web
particularly Jordan Peterson an idea was
touched on that I thought you might like
to expand on it seems the fact that dr.
Peterson actually embodies his
philosophy to a rare degree is
particularly confounding to his
detractors the character attacks
misrepresentation flat-out lies about
him and his message is this evidence of
a disdain for not just the individual
but also for what he represents I think
yes
what do you think I think yes yeah I
think there's a really interesting
concept here which is about congruence
and which is about living one's message
out in the world because I agree very
very few people actually live out their
philosophy in the world and to a lesser
degree or a similar degree they're
actually they're actually is is a
representation of the
sort of the word psychological
necessities on one level like I think it
he talked about yawn and the idea of the
conjunction yeah something conjunction
the conjunction mysterious mysterium
conjunction the other mysterio
conjunction I think where it's about a
deeper and deeper process of embodiment
of your ideas in terms of your actions
yeah and then a deeper integration of
different perspectives and finally I
think an integration of the masculine
and feminine aspects of oneself that is
kind of the process of individuation and
I do think that that sense of someone
who's really living out their ideas in
the world and is living from that very
deep place of true accountability and
general and genuine like I find a route
I find a real yeah real integrity I do
think does trigger people who are not
living from that place yeah and I think
it kind of on some subconscious level
calls them out yeah and I think that's
that's part of the reactivity to him
it's because he's a walking rebuke to
people who are not actually living out
their philosophy in the world yeah I
thought was I think that's wrong because
there's especially the kind of message
of self responsibility
that's what like he said in the recent
interview you did a left last week
actually not should we put this bit out
yet but he does preview he does mention
you know especially with with radical
people on the left and the example he
was using was like have you really taken
full ownership of yourself and of your
own individuality or are you projecting
it outwards that was a question yeah I
don't just say yes because it's all
hardest things to do so don't assume
that you have exactly and that's the
point it is constant work like kind of
inner
growth work and embodiment work it's
constant work I means like everyday work
and it's also the sense that
post-modernism is a like many people I
felt this a long time before I even
discovered Peterson is it's you get into
an argument for someone who claims there
is no truth and it's performative
contradiction because they're arguing
from a perspective there's no truth it's
like okay so that's your truth that
truth and also that you cannot there are
certain things about especially the
philosophy post-modernism that you
cannot live out in the world
yeah you can't you can't spend any time
at all believing there's no truth and if
you I think this is Jonathan pathos
really clever way of framing it's like
well if if if you're a dedicated post
modernist and I come up to you and I say
I've just seen your partner having
dinner with someone down the road and
they look very intimate you're not gonna
say well there was no truth yeah and
your body is gonna tell you certain
things yes like well yeah I I've got
very high sort of share with Peter and a
frustration of people who claim to have
a philosophy that they're not actually
living out in their in their lives yeah
that's yeah that's a really good point
there's also that this this thing of
victimhood culture which is rampant he
he stands us completely something that
challenges that actually and teaching
meditation I I often say the one thing
that drops from your vocabulary when you
start meditating is I couldn't help it
you know this whole thing of like
trigger warning so triggered I just
can't you know that is that can that can
go with practice and I can go with
taking personal responsibility for your
own inner world and that there was a
hard process so it's easier to stay in
the victim thing and then to the point
you made the beginning of this question
then you start projecting it out to
wherever you see it embodied the thing
you don't have or the thing that you're
rejecting is embody just so pushing it
out so I think yeah so yes we agree we
agree we also force number nine
a forbidden question that no one can
talk about oh god we shouldn't read over
Louise brought this up and I think it's
very important question where our
women's long form deep insights and
opinions about the pieces of movement ie
Jungian psychology motivations political
issues men's movement open dialog about
societal problems etc etc it seems women
are not participating in these long form
discussions or am i rolling in there in
an echo chamber I really want to know
the other side of the equation they're
deep insights from a female perspective
likewise I really want to as well yeah
we certainly haven't been actually those
question to you oh yeah no but yeah I'm
just gonna repeat that as well no it's a
really I also I'm really curious about
this and that we have you know some
amazing women in our circles who are
engaged at these type of ideas very
happy to talk about them and I wonder if
it's a question of the the format of
like you know most of the stuff is
happening on YouTube people really
putting themselves out there whether
that's got something to do with it
whether these conversations are
happening somewhere else
whether the confident maybe the
conversation around the current form of
feminism is so loud that it makes being
a woman and saying anything a little bit
different like Louise did those previous
interviews quite a risky thing to do mmm
maybe arguably more risky for a woman
than a man I don't know yeah so the next
question is from James Carmichael and
James you've shortened it a little bit
but James tells quite a touching story
of having been born with visually
impaired and then having experiences in
school where you would always have
support from the teachers and when you
try to talk about that being
uncomfortable for you the way it was
given they kind of as you put it
you were given a shut up because we know
what's best look and then you go on to
talk about your father passing away when
you're 22 and feeling like your own only
real masculine anchor was severed
said during and after his death my
coping mechanism turned it to alcohol
smoking and drugs I'm 31 now and really
trying putting effort into understanding
why I'm like this and what I can do
about it
and over the last few years I've made
some great progress due to jordan
peterson and many other figures like
that however i can't shake this feeling
that i'm wasted my 20s trying to avoid
the pain and anger through booze etc and
I'm worried that my youth is slowly
slipping through my fingers with nothing
to show for it they need bison what I
could do to accelerate the healing
process books practical physical mental
exercises etc thanks and sorry for long
read no worries man hmm I think this was
the question that people voted up the
most yes hi and yeah I wanna say thank
you for sharing that James and yeah I
think the the level of personal insight
the already showing by sharing in that
way is showing that you're you're on the
right track and because there's a lot of
people stuck in in pretty crappy
situations that can't really articulate
it and yeah I think at least being able
to articulate is it is a good start I
yeah I want to say that like if it's we
can we can give a little bit of an
advice but if if what you're dealing
with the moment is kind of alcohol and
and drugs then alcohol and drugs and
therapy aana it could be something to
look at
grief counseling as well because early
that you said your father died about
nine years ago I certainly found when my
father died but I needed to go through
some serious yeah getting a letting a
lot of the emotions out in terms of like
if you're if you're generally pretty
stable then I'd say the thing that has
been the most rewarding for me is a
men's group where we have to teach men's
work and we're in a we're in a kind of
men's circle together and just to have
this space to really speak
what's real what's true what's authentic
with other men I think is really
important and I think men in particular
we're now quite aware we can become very
isolated and get older and it's very
easy for us to become isolated and also
I think to look for support in women and
girlfriends that actually we need to be
finding outside the relationship to
resources for the relationship yeah it's
not not that we should talk about some
things but the balance I think is all
wrong if we're looking for all of our
sustenance from the entire relationship
yeah you end up making your partner like
your mom in that sense which is not not
the right way to go about it yeah so I
would just add to that and like yeah
thank you for yeah for communicating now
this is courageous thing to do just to
echo what David said yeah I mean I think
traditional therapies especially the
right therapists are very important if
it is something that is substance abuse
or grief etc and then from a kind of
place where you feel stable which you
might be already we can't tell just from
a comment men's work I would also put in
meditation because meditation is really
core practice for connecting to yourself
for knowing yourself also can be very
relaxing if you use it for that too and
yeah men circle for sure in terms of
books ones that were good for me warrior
king magician lover is like one of the
original is written in the 70s it's a
more modern nineties is the night is
okay yeah well it's aged well even well
even if it is from the 90s that's a good
kind of foundational one and quite
accessible and stoicism yeah for sure
Marcus Aurelius and yes Stoics as you've
already said that Jordan Peterson's
helped yeah and the stoic said he's
stoic take on life yes that's good yeah
do you have any plans to more
specifically have integral theory spiral
dynamics meta modern discussions with
any of the guests you have either prior
guests or upcoming ones yes we have
actually some solace from kellyco tmh is
who asked that we actually have some
already recorded integral conversations
and are talking about having some more
with some pretty significant integral
thinkers yeah mysterious yeah yeah I'm
yet for people who don't know I think
pretty much everyone who's watched our
videos so far knows that we've got quite
a kind of yeah we've got to risk a lot
of respect for the integral lens yes
there's a kind of developmental model of
consciousness and yeah so we do where
this has always been this was something
that had a huge influence on us reading
Trump in the post truth world after the
election of Trump was Ken Wilbur's ebook
and yeah we have something coming up
next week it was next week isn't it yeah
yeah we had a discussion with Jeff
Salzmann of The Daily Evolver that some
time ago now but we were gonna put it
out next week with the series Jordan
Pederson on the left as a as a kind of
integral take on Jordan Pederson yeah so
yeah we were definitely gonna do more of
that and number 12 number 12 from Alavi
I've read some comments about the men's
getaway that rebel wisdom runs and they
characterize it in rebel wisdom as a
brand of feminism is that a fair thing
to say and how do those counts relate to
the current dichotomy of gender politics
feminism the third wave and the second
wave based liberal feminism and then in
brackets hot summer and Paglia and men's
rights activism and Peter stone Ian
men's advocacy and then in brackets
Peterson rejecting feminism and
outlining the poor state of masculinity
and manhood and a way forward for men
so his rebel wisdom a brand of feminism
that's though that's the key question
there was someone who commented on most
of our early videos saying watch out men
these are crypto radical feminists
fairplay term he was very persistent he
was very persistent yeah and it's really
interesting we've actually just come
back from America we've got a whole load
of content we're gonna be putting out
around masculinity fairly soon
we spoke to Warren Farrell who is kind
of known as the godfather of the the the
men's movement well the men's rights
movement although I think that's
slightly unfair because I don't really
he's synonymous with the men's rights
movement he's he's a he's a therapist
and a deep thinker and someone who was
part of the the feminist movement itself
in the 70s and then broke with them over
certain ideological difficulties he had
with whip with feminism as it was
developing but it's interesting we asked
him about this question he saying look
we a lot what seems to trigger this guy
in particular and summer some other men
is any tell or any talk about Maine
getting in touch with their emotions
triggers them immediately into that's
women's talk that's feminism it's like I
find it entirely bizarre I find that
whole perspective really bizarre yeah
the idea it just seems incredibly you
know just seems incredibly narrow their
definition of what masculinity is I I
would not yeah I our work is not only
our work is about emotional health like
saying things that you because that's
coverage it's also parity I'll talk
about what's really good so I see that
as a as a as a masculine trait just as
much as it's a kind of emotional
intelligence feminine trait but also
that's not that's not all that our
workshops are about as well yeah it's
also about a really deep sense of
connector to the masculine energy the
masculine Drive the life force making
friends with our anger using that as
fuel and our lives integrating so I
certainly not a this is a difficult
question when someone says are you a
feminist because it's usually a barb
it's usually a hook yeah because there's
no right answer to that and to remain in
polite society yeah because you have to
give the same art to the Jordan Pederson
would give which is if you're saying
wouldn't it be great for men and women
to be able to offer their skills from
from from an equal basis absolutely
anything less is it's crazy yeah if it's
the idea that the world is a corrupt
patriarchy and men need to atone for
that and no that's ideology and that's
not something that I'm into yeah yeah
likewise just on that point I have a
very similar feeling around that
question I've never described myself as
a feminist but then again of course of
course I want equality of opportunity
and I think it's important to strive for
that but as the ideology and as the
conspiracy theory no and as thick the
the way it's turned into kind of
castration and shaming of the masculine
actually find that like I'm really
really not okay with that and I find
that a lot of the men you comfort of
workshops as well have internalized that
to the degree to a large degree often
all of us have to some extent and part
of the work we do is it's going through
that and coming out and it kind of
grounded in body confident and relaxed
masculinity yeah honestly that those
comments early pissed me off from that
guy and it's interesting that it's come
up you know that's someone's read them
because yeah for a similar reason to
what you you laid out it's this I can
understand and would agree with like
that the nice guy thing of men being
like really overly vulnerable all the
time to kind of score points or because
that's like oh that's it thank you
that's the way to have sex with girls
that also probably doesn't I'm sure
worked a couple of times for them but
like that is really not yeah
I'm not about that at all but being
being in touch with your emotions is
absolutely essential
and it's what the this kind of reaction
against that from from a few people for
me that's that's boy a boyish victimhood
mmm it's not it's not for me I look at
that I don't think it's manly I don't
know what should black mic for I don't
know any women who would look at that
and find that sexy or empowering or
strong it would just be like there's
something unresolved there yeah yeah and
aporia now we forgot to we forgot to set
a clock before we started doing this so
we yeah yeah it's wanted to conclude
that by saying we've we've actually
renamed our weekend workshop a new
masculinity yeah so we are I think what
we're offering is where we're placing it
is within an evolutionary framework of
responding to the to the the rise of
feminism but not from a and I find too
much of the root of the men's rights
activist movement is in reactivity to
that feminism like it's it's saying well
these angry women in feminism but it's
it's got a real Lang it's got a real
wreck reactivity to it and a real anger
of its own and it can easily just become
another victim story
yeah like women women did this to me
yeah rather than an empowering taking
responsibility for ourselves on a
narrative and so that that is how we're
framing it we're framing it as as
offering and I think that has to be in a
space of personal growth that has to be
a space of sort of really embodying our
masculinity and because because also
what we're then fighting against this
kind of gender neutrality of well there
is no such thing as masculinity and
femininity it's all gender neutral and
we sort of plant a flag and say no
that's not true
yeah and your deep embodied reality is
as a man in my experience for myself
certainly most of the men that we've had
in our workshops there is something
tangible as a
we can tap into the is it is it is
something that when we ground ourselves
in that we find our relationships with
women improve yeah and other men and but
everyone pretty much more present and
more authentic which creates trust in
men or women yeah yeah great and then so
there were a lot of amazing questions
and we've done 12 I think there were 100
comments so yeah thank you everybody and
on that note a couple people asked quite
rightly like whether there can be some
kind of chat or some way for us to
continue this conversation all together
in some forum and there is now because
we have created a discord and in the
show notes for this will be the link so
click it if you want to join or our hope
is to create quite a thriving community
where we can bounce ideas back and forth
where we can yeah explore the content
we're putting up suggest new content
just debate get to know one another
yeah and I'm personally really looking
forward to that to be cool and I hope
you'll join us great thank you
you